Guide to the Elizabeth Donnan Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elizabeth Donnan papers
1806-1863
MS 184
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Manuscripts and typewritten copies of newspaper articles, ships' logs and letterbooks in the Library of Congress relating to the slave trade after 1806, especially during the years 1810-1811, 1816-1821 and 1860-1863. These were collected but not used in connection with her Documents Illustrative of the Slave Trade, published 1930-1934.
Donnan, Elizabeth, 1883-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Elizabeth Donnan, 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Elizabeth Donnan Papers consist of copies of letter books, ship logs, and newspaper articles relating to the slave trade after 1806. The originals are in the Library of Congress. The years 1810-1811, 1816-1821, 1850, and 1860-1863 are most fully represented. According to a handwritten note sent with the papers Professor Donnan never used the notes for any of her publications.
Biographical / Historical
Educated at Cornell University and Wellesley College; author of Documents Illustrative of the Slave Trade to America (4 vols.) 1930-1934, Economic Principles and Modern Practice (with H.R. Mussey) 1942.
African Americans; Slave trade; Authors; Educators; Donnan, Elizabeth, 1883-1955
- Inventory
  - Reports and notes on slave trade and slave ships, 1804-1807, 1810-1811 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Niles' Register, 1816-1821 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Library of Congress American Colonization Society, 1826-1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library of Congress American Colonization Society, 1835-1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Library of Congress American Colonization Society. Papers of A. H. Foote, 1840-1850 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Library of Congress, Letter Book of Andrew H. Foote, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
  - Library of Congress, Letter Book of Andrew H. Foote, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers. J. C. Van Dyke, 1854, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1860-1862 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Library of Congress Slave Papers and Slave Trade, Vol I, 1864-1870 (Box 1, Folder 16)